<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<channel>
 <item>
<article>

    <section>
        <parent>News</parent>
        <child>Africa</child>
    </section>
  <title><![CDATA[30 killed in ambush on wedding convoy in Nigeria]]></title>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <description><![CDATA[  Gunmen have attacked a wedding convoy in Nigeria&#039;s northeastern state of Borno, killing more than 30 people.]]></description>
  <articleDate>Sunday, November 3 2013 16:43:18 GMT+0200


</articleDate>
  <story>
      <![CDATA[  <p>MAIDUGURI</p><p>Gunmen have attacked a wedding convoy in Nigeria's northeastern state of Borno, killing more than 30 people including the groom in a suspected ambush, witnesses and survivors said Sunday.</p><p>The attack happened on Saturday on the notorious Bama-Banki road when the wedding party, including friends and relatives of the groom, was making its way back to the state capital Maiduguri after the ceremony in Michika, in nearby in Adamawa State, they said.</p><p>"It was a gory scene," said a driver, who said he had seen the dead bodies on the highway.</p><p>GUNSHOT WOUNDS</p><p>The driver, who did not wish to be named, told AFP that many of the victims appeared to have suffered gunshot wounds.</p><p>"All the victims were brutally murdered by the attackers. My passengers and I were visibly shocked when we met the dead bodies lying by the highway," he said.</p><p>Army and police officials in the area were not immediately available for comment. But a security source who described the incident as "brutal and callous" said the bodies had been transferred to a hospital in Maiduguri.</p><p>Violent attacks are not uncommon in northeastern Nigeria, where the army has launched an offensive to end an insurgency by Boko Haram Islamists.</p>]]>
  </story>
  <author>
      <![CDATA[AFP -1]]>
    </author>
  </article>

<media>
    <photo><![CDATA[http://cdn.marcellus.tv/0/xml/images/BornoMap.jpg]]></photo>
      <caption><![CDATA[

MAP | GOOGLE]]></caption>
      </media>
<link>
    http://www.nation.co.ke/news/africa/Borno-Nigeria-Gunmen-Attack-Wedding/-/1066/2058604/-/hgtyyb/-/index.html</link>
</item><item>
<article>

    <section>
        <parent>News</parent>
        <child>Africa</child>
    </section>
  <title><![CDATA[DRC army launches assault on last rebel holdouts]]></title>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <description><![CDATA[  The Democratic Republic of Congo army said it has launched a new offensive against rebels.]]></description>
  <articleDate>Sunday, November 3 2013 14:57:51 GMT+0200


</articleDate>
  <story>
      <![CDATA[  <p>KIWANJA</p><p>The Democratic Republic of Congo army said Sunday it has launched a new offensive against rebel fighters who fled to the hills after being ousted from their last stronghold.</p><p>"We are pounding Mbuzi," one of three mountains in eastern DR Congo where the rebels are hiding, General Lucien Bahuma told AFP by telephone. "After the artillery we will send in the troops."</p><p>Some 200 die-hard fighters of the M23 rebel group have been holed up in the mountainous region bordering Uganda since their base in the town of Bunagana was seized on Wednesday.</p><p>"They are claiming back the hills. There is shooting in the mountains of Ntamugena, Mbuzi and Runyonyi. The rebels are fleeing," a DR Congo captain told AFP, speaking anonymously.</p><p>The sound of heavy artillery could be heard from Kiwanja, a town around 20 kilometres (12 miles) away.</p><p>STAMP OUT INSURGENCY</p><p>The lush green hilly region bordering Uganda has been rocked by heavy fighting for the past 10 days as army troops battle to stamp out the insurgency once and for all in the restive, mineral rich North Kivu province.</p><p>The clashes have forced thousands from their fields and homes, and aid agencies estimate some 10,000 refugees have streamed into Uganda.</p><p>'There was a lot of shooting'</p><p>In a muddy field barely a kilometre inside the Ugandan border, hundreds of Congolese sheltered from the rain under plastic sheets.</p><p>Among them Noella Bigumashyaka, a 26-year-old teacher from the village of Jomba who fled for Uganda on Wednesday.</p><p>"I have two of my children with me, but I don't know what happened to the other two, they are only five and eight," she said weeping.</p><p>"There was a lot of shooting. We ran too quickly, abandoned our belongings along the road. We're dirty but we can't change our clothes."</p><p>For some it was not the first time they had to flee fighting in the notoriously unstable region which has seen two major wars in the past two decades fought over control of the former Belgian colony's mineral resources.</p><p>Jean-Nepomuscene Twizerimana recalled having to leave his home as a child in 1998, when fighting raged between two rebel groups, the Tutsi RCD and the extremist Hutu FDLR, and again in 2005 as well as last year when the M23 rebels moved in.</p><p>"When the M23 were there we were under the authority of rebels, people were miserable, because there was no peace," the 20-year-old said.</p><p>"But now the government has come in and nothing has changed... because we are now refugees here."</p><p>The M23 movement was founded by ethnic Tutsi former rebels who were incorporated into the Congolese army under a 2009 peace deal but then mutinied in April 2012, claiming that the pact had never been fully implemented.</p><p>At their strongest in November last year, M23 marched into Goma, a mining hub and city of one million people, and took control for 10 days, before regional leaders persuaded them into fresh peace talks.</p><p>But the stop-start talks fell apart last month when Kinshasa refused amnesty for about 80 rebel leaders and the DR Congo army -- backed by a special United Nations force -- went on the attack in a bid to end the rebellion.</p>]]>
  </story>
  <author>
      <![CDATA[AFP -1]]>
    </author>
  </article>

<media>
    <photo><![CDATA[http://cdn.marcellus.tv/0/xml/images/644266-01-02.JPG.jpg]]></photo>
      <caption><![CDATA[

PHOTO | JUNIOR D.KANNAH Congolese refugees, returning from Uganda, walk back home on November 1, 2013, in Bunagana, 99 kms from the eastern Democratic Republic of Congo city of Goma, at the frontier with Uganda.]]></caption>
      </media>
<link>
    http://www.nation.co.ke/news/africa/Democratic-Republic-of-Congo-M23-Rebels-Strongholds/-/1066/2058518/-/xagu1qz/-/index.html</link>
</item><item>
<article>

    <section>
        <parent>News</parent>
        <child>Politics</child>
    </section>
  <title><![CDATA[Cotu adds voice to uproar over media Bill]]></title>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <description><![CDATA[  The Central Organisation of Trade Unions has welcomed President Kenyatta’s promise to seek media organisations’ input on the media Bill.]]></description>
  <articleDate>Sunday, November 3 2013 13:53:59 GMT+0200


</articleDate>
  <story>
      <![CDATA[  <p>The Central Organisation of Trade Unions has welcomed President Uhuru Kenyatta’s promise to seek media organisations’ input before appending his signature on a controversial Bill geared towards hampering press freedom.</p><p>The organisation said it was encouraged by the President’s immediate reaction to the proposed law that, if passed, would roll back gains made in the media circles.</p><p>Cotu Secretary-General Francis Atwoli also criticised the hurried draconian amendments to the Kenya Communication (amendment) Bill adopted by MPs on Thursday. (EDITORIAL: <a href="http://www.nation.co.ke/oped/Editorial/Second-assault-on-media-by-MPs-baffling/-/440804/2057940/-/r2n090/-/index.html">Second assault on media by MPs baffling</a>)</p><p>“Let us not operate retrogressively. This parliament has young people who should be championing for social justice through the media instead of bringing up laws to muzzle them,” said Mr Atwoli on Sunday at the Sarova Stanley Hotel in Nairobi. </p><p>He added that the media was the only institution that will help the nation remain relevant to the challenges bedevilling it.</p><p>“Any country without justice is not a state. We can only champion for the aspirations of the common people through a vibrant media,” said Mr Atwoli at the function organised by the Buchero Education and Development Fund.</p><p>'GO SLOW'</p><p>The Chairman of the Council of Governors Isaac Ruto also condemned the Bill saying it took the country backwards after making remarkable progress in media freedom. He urged for dialogue between the media practitioners and the MPs to avert unwarranted media oppression.</p><p>“I do not think we need such a Bill now. In the last parliament we passed a law that allowed media to regulate themselves. I would like to urge Majority Leader (Aden) Duale to go slow on this and not use the numbers in the House to terrorise the media,” said Mr Ruto.</p><p>On Saturday, President Kenyatta said he would engage various media stakeholders in looking at the contentious sections before signing the proposed law.</p><p>The journalists through the Kenya Editors Guild, Kenya Union of Journalists and the Kenya Correspondents Association have said the Bill is unconstitutional and should not have been passed by parliament. </p><p>“The contents of this Bill are an affront to freedom of expression not only to with respect to the media fraternity but with respect to all Kenyans. The Bill is therefore unconstitutional and we call upon President Kenyatta not to sign it into law,” said the associations in a joint statement read by Editors Guild vice-chairman David Ohito.</p><p>They accused the MPs of reneging on agreements arrived by the media and the committee when they met to discuss the contentious clauses of the proposed law.  (READ: <a href="http://www.nation.co.ke/news/Uhuru-welcomes-debate-on-media-bill-law/-/1056/2057888/-/10vu8au/-/index.html">Uhuru welcomes debate on the proposed media law</a>)</p><p>“From the look of things, the National Assembly has chosen to misuse its legislative powers to re-introduce draconian laws meant to gag the media and muzzle all critical voices that seek to hold power to account,” added the journalists.</p>]]>
  </story>
  <author>
      <![CDATA[JEREMIAH KIPLANG'AT -1]]>
    </author>
  </article>

<media>
    <photo><![CDATA[http://cdn.marcellus.tv/0/xml/images/DnMediaPress3110.JPG.jpg]]></photo>
      <caption><![CDATA[

PHOTO | FILE Journalists protest over the controversial media Bill.]]></caption>
      </media>
<link>
    http://www.nation.co.ke/news/politics/Central-Organisation-of-Trade-Unions-Francis-Atwoli-Media-Bill/-/1064/2058448/-/67vjel/-/index.html</link>
</item><item>
<article>

    <section>
        <parent>News</parent>
        <child>Africa</child>
    </section>
  <title><![CDATA[Abyei: The hidden hand of the past]]></title>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <description><![CDATA[  Two things happened early this week in the disputed Abyei region of the Sudan.]]></description>
  <articleDate>Sunday, November 3 2013 11:56:35 GMT+0200


</articleDate>
  <story>
      <![CDATA[  <p>Two things happened early this week in the disputed Abyei region of the Sudan: one community voted to join south Sudan, the other announced the vote was a declaration of war.</p><p>A unilateral referendum that had been organised by the Dinka-Ngok showed the community nearly voted to the last man to join South Sudan. An overwhelming 99.9 per cent of the voters wanted the region to be declared part of the south. Only 12 of the 63,433 voters that turned out wanted the region to remain in Sudan. (READ: <a href="http://www.nation.co.ke/news/africa/Over-99-pct-of-Abyeis-Dinka-vote-to-join-South-Sudan/-/1066/2056862/-/uw2fn3/-/index.html">Over 99 pct of Abyei's Dinka vote to join South Sudan</a>)</p><p>“It was a peaceful, transparent and fair exercise. Our people have expressed their opinion to join South Sudan,” said Mr Deng Biong Mijak, the Head of the legal team of the commission that organised the vote told reporters afterwards.</p><p>“I believe some will accept, some are not even vocal now,” he said in reference to whether the outcome will be recognised. He was right, except that the vote was only accepted by the voters.</p><p>The vote was rejected by Sudan, the African Union and the United Nations and the story of when Abyei would be declared part of South Sudan or Sudan continues to be an epic saga. This problem was part of the issues to be tackled when the Comprehensive Peace Agreement (brokered by Kenya) between Sudan and the then Sudan People’s Liberation Movement under the late John Garang. (READ: <a href="http://www.nation.co.ke/news/africa/Abyei-Vote-Referendum-African-Union/-/1066/2052570/-/6sitjqz/-/index.html">AU boss calls for rejection of vote over the future of disputed Abyei</a>)</p><p>Khartoum rejected the vote because it argued the Misseriya nomads did not take part in it (Omar al-Bashir hopes they will vote for Sudan). On the other hand, South Sudan accepted the vote because of the nine Dinka Ngok chiefdoms which were transferred in 1905 to vote in line with the July 22, 2009 ruling of the Permanent Court of Arbitration in The Hague.</p><p>When Sudan and the Sudan People’s Liberation Movement took the Abyei matter before the Permanent Court of Arbitration, five arbitrators led by Judge Pierre-Marie Dupuuy observed that:</p><blockquote><p>“The Tribunal understands that both Parties accept that, under a predominantly tribal interpretation, in order to determine the area of the nine Ngok Dinka chiefdoms transferred to Kordofan in 1905, the location of the Ngok Dinka in 1905 must be established.”</p></blockquote><p>The judges decided to define Abyei as the land of the Dinka Ngok but gave the nomadic Misseriya the rights to graze their animals on both sides of the Sudan. They declined to draw boundaries of the region arguing that it should be part of the reconciliation contained in the CPA.</p><p>COLONIAL ORIGINS</p><p>On the face of it; it appears the conflict is between the Dinka Ngok and the Misseriya, but analysts of the conflict say the seeds were sowed during the colonial times.</p><p>When Egyptians and the British jointly decided to colonise Sudan in 1899, they changed territories of the communities, and sometimes those communities found themselves living astride others’ traditional lands. Prof Maurice Amutabi, a cultural historian on African affairs and the current Deputy Vice-Chancellor of Kisii University thinks this dominance plays today in Abyei.</p><p>“The tensions in Abyei right now are the result of moving boundaries between Arabs and black Africans. Going by a historical view of it, Abyei would be part and parcel of South Sudan. But then these two communities were pushed into each other,” he told the Sunday Nation on Friday.</p><p>During colonial times, Abyei was administratively transferred to the Kordofan in the present-day Sudan in 1905 by the British colonial administration. Historical data shows the Dinka Ngok were occupants at the time, while the Arab Misseriya were nomads coming in and out seasonally.</p><p>The colonial administration, historians say, thought the disputes between the raiders and the victims could easily be resolved if they were reporting to one authority, a governor of Kordofan.Although divisions between the Dinka Ngok and the Misseriya remained, the two were put under the same constituency with the Misseriya dominating subsequent elections due to their alliance with the politically active al-Mahdi family.</p><p>“Abyei is a classic example of lumping together communities without considering their history. The colonialists did not take cognisance of the social lives of the two communities,” argued Mr Ngari Gatuku, a cultural analyst and commentator on African affairs in Nairobi.</p><p>“Secondly, each community had a particular relationship with one another and they knew how to handle their differences. When the arbitrary territorial umbrella came in, it spoilt it all,” he added.</p><p>Historically, animosity between the two sides worsened after the 1965 Massacre when more than 100 Dinka Ngok people were killed followed by the occupation by the nomads as the Dinka were displaced. This led to a rebellion in 1983 led by Dr Garang.</p><p>The war between the South and the North ideally ceased in 2005 after the CPA that proposed a referendum for the south to separate. The Ngok youth were part of this. In 2011, South Sudanese voted to form a new country.</p><p>But a referendum that should have been conducted alongside that of South Sudan on whether Abyei remains in Kordofan or joins the south failed because the two parties could not agree on who should vote.</p><p>Experts insist a referendum would be the only way to handle the problem, but how to go about it is the problem.</p><p>“It has worked in Yemen and many other parts of the world before. It should work with Abyei. I understand the region has several oil wells and the current tensions are no longer just about boundaries but about which side will take the oil,” Prof Amutabi argued. “Truth of the matter is there is a nomadic community which means the role of water and drought should be considered.”</p><p>Dr Doughlas Johnson, an expert on the South Sudan-Sudan conflict says that if the resolution of the Abyei conflict is to be true to the declaration in the Machakos Protocol that it will address the “root causes” of the problem, then it must provide a way to redress the balance between the displaced Ngok population and the seasonal migrant Misseriya population.</p><p>“It must also address the anxieties of the Misseriya about their future access to pastures and waterways that have become increasingly vital to the survival of their herds.”</p><p>Reported by AGGREY MUTAMBO in Nairobi and MACHEL AMOS in Juba.</p>]]>
  </story>
  <author>
      <![CDATA[AGGREY MUTAMBO -1]]>
    </author>
  </article>

<media>
    <photo><![CDATA[http://cdn.marcellus.tv/0/xml/images/636363-01-02.JPG.jpg]]></photo>
      <caption><![CDATA[

PHOTO | ALI NGETHI Votes are counted in a polling station after a referendum in the disputed Abyei region of Sudan on October 30, 2013.]]></caption>
      </media>
<link>
    http://www.nation.co.ke/news/africa/Sudan-Referendum-Abye/-/1066/2058318/-/kygnb3z/-/index.html</link>
</item><item>
<article>

    <section>
        <parent>Home</parent>
        <child>News</child>
    </section>
  <title><![CDATA[Psychologists warn of lasting effects after Westgate attack]]></title>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <description><![CDATA[  A team of psychologists want the government to put in place proper measures of dealing with the effect of disasters.]]></description>
  <articleDate>Sunday, November 3 2013 11:5:18 GMT+0200


</articleDate>
  <story>
      <![CDATA[  <p>A team of psychologists who have been helping counsel survivors of the Westgate attack now want the government to put in place proper measures of dealing with the effect of disasters on the mental health of survivors.</p><p>In their report, the Kenya Psychological Association (KPA) warns that the longterm mental effect of the incident, like many others before it, could be devastating unless proper counselling system is put in place.</p><p>“There is need for planning with proper structures put in place to ensure that we address the past array of psychological needs relating to terror and guarantee preparedness for the future,” the team says in a document titled Report on the Westgate Trauma Psychosocial Support Programme.</p><p>The specialists state that while the Westgate Mall attack has “negatively impacted the emotional health of the Kenyan people,” the consistent pattern with which survivors of previous terror attacks were left on their own is a worrying trend that could lead to future social problems.</p><p>“We are finding out that many survivors of the 1998 bombing and previous other attacks have never fully healed. The nation has remained psychologically unprepared for terror attacks for the reason that proper structures have been absent in Kenya in anticipation of such eventualities.”</p><p>On September 21, terrorists laid siege to the Westgate Mall leading to the deaths of at least 70 people with hundreds others injured. Although many of those injured were treated and discharged, the Kenya Red Cross in conjunction with KPA employed 400 psychologists and counsellors to help provide what they called ‘Psychological First-Aid.’</p><p>The KPA in conjunction with the Kenya Red Cross set up trauma centres at the Oshwal Centre, and later at Uhuru Park, from where teams were sent to various hospitals in Nairobi to act side by side with medics who were attending to the injured. At Oshwal, survivors were rushed in from Westgate for quick first aid before being taken to hospitals for further treatment.</p><p>They assisted survivors of the attack, relatives and friends of the dead and injured, soldiers, the police and volunteers including the Kenya Red Cross team itself.</p><p>MORE PHASES</p><p>According to Dr Gladys K Mwiti, the KPA chairperson and a member of the Board of Directors for the International Society for Traumatic Stress Studies, this initial counselling was only meant to establish a path to recovery but was not enough. The Westgate attack saw about 3,000 survivors and relatives counselled although the report says that there is a need for another two phases to be done.</p><p>“The first thing we did in this first aid was to ask people what their need was, someone may say ‘my child is missing’, someone may say ‘my property has just gone up in the fire’. After listening to their need and offering comfort and hope, the individual was connected to where they can get that help,” Dr Mwiti told the Nation.</p><p>But the team reports that even those not directly affected by the attack were helped. They include journalists, security agents and volunteers; some of the people who witnessed the attack and aftermath first.</p><p>“It is very clear that follow-up is needed if those affected by the attack and the general populace is to heal,” Dr Mwiti said in a report she co-presented with her colleagues Sammy Wambugu, a Counselling Psychologist and Dr Oscar Githua, a Forensic Psychologist.</p><p>“The people our team met and counselled were in pain, grief, stress, had lost appetite, were anxious, reported headaches and insomnia, mood swings, poor concentration and some are in self-blame.</p><p>“In psychological terms, the danger that lurks after the Westgate attack is even greater as it has the capacity to break the very fabric and harmony in our society. The attack could definitely incubate mass depression, trauma and even conflict between the main religious groups in Kenya.”</p><p>The experts warn that if this is left untouched, “suicide, hallucinations and delusions, depression, suicidal tendencies, chronic anxiety and fatigue, hostility, hypersensitivity, eating disorders such as anorexia or obesity, and other obsessive behaviours” could befall the survivors.</p>]]>
  </story>
  <author>
      <![CDATA[AGGREY MUTAMBO -1]]>
    </author>
  </article>

<media>
    <photo><![CDATA[http://cdn.marcellus.tv/0/xml/images/DN_Nakuru_Westgate_2809+b.JPG.jpg]]></photo>
      <caption><![CDATA[

PHOTO | SULEIMAN MBATIAH | FILE A Nakuru resident during a ceremony in memory of the victims of the Westgate attack on September 27, 2013.]]></caption>
      </media>
<link>
    http://www.nation.co.ke/news/Westgate-Attack-Trauma-Psychologists/-/1056/2058270/-/syxywsz/-/index.html</link>
</item><item>
<article>

    <section>
        <parent>Home</parent>
        <child>News</child>
    </section>
  <title><![CDATA[One dead, 49 injured in Ngara accident]]></title>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <description><![CDATA[  At least one person was killed and 49 others injured in an accident along Kipande road in Ngara.]]></description>
  <articleDate>Sunday, November 3 2013 10:6:52 GMT+0200


</articleDate>
  <story>
      <![CDATA[  <p>At least one person was killed and 49 others injured in an accident along Kipande road in Ngara, Nairobi on Sunday when a bus belonging to Kisii Classic company crashed into a wall and four cars which were parked at the Uzuri Institute compound.</p><p>The injured were taken to Kenyatta National Hospital with eight people in critical condition.</p><p>The accident occurred in the early hours of the morning, with St John Ambulance responding at 4:30 am.</p>]]>
  </story>
  <author>
      <![CDATA[NATION REPORTER -1]]>
    </author>
  </article>

<media>
    <photo><![CDATA[http://cdn.marcellus.tv/0/xml/images/Kipande.jpg]]></photo>
      <caption><![CDATA[

MAP | GOOGLE]]></caption>
      </media>
<link>
    http://www.nation.co.ke/news/Ngara-Nairobi-Kisii-Classic-Bus-Crash/-/1056/2058236/-/fwcf3gz/-/index.html</link>
</item><item>
<article>

    <section>
        <parent>News</parent>
        <child>Politics</child>
    </section>
  <title><![CDATA[Ruto returns from The Hague]]></title>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <description><![CDATA[  Deputy President William Ruto on Sunday returned to the country from The Hague.]]></description>
  <articleDate>Sunday, November 3 2013 8:55:51 GMT+0200


</articleDate>
  <story>
      <![CDATA[  <p>Deputy President William Ruto on Sunday returned to the country from The Hague after the International Criminal Court on Friday excused him from attending his trial this week.</p><p>The plane carrying Mr Ruto touched down at the Jomo Kenyatta International Airport at 6:30 am.</p><p>Mr Ruto will be in charge of government affairs until Wednesday as President Uhuru Kenyatta begins a three-day official visit to South Africa. The Trial Chamber V (a) also allowed Mr Ruto to miss the sittings on Thursday and Friday as he will be chairing a refugee and drought meeting in Nairobi. (READ: <a href="http://www.nation.co.ke/news/politics/Uhuru-to-leave-for-SA-as-Ruto-jets-in-to-run-State-affairs--/-/1064/2057750/-/xqmm2x/-/index.html">Uhuru to leave for SA as Ruto jets in to run State affairs</a>)</p><p>Reasons for Mr Ruto's excusal will be provided on Monday. Presiding judge Chile Eboe-Osuji said that the decision to grant the request was unanimous. “The Chamber has deliberated on the Ruto request,” Mr Osuji said on Friday. “The chamber unanimously grants the request.”</p><p>However, the chamber on Friday rejected Joshua Sang’s application to be allowed to attend his daughter’s graduation.</p><p>The Deputy President was received by Lands Cabinet Secretary Charity Ngilu, senior government officials and Members of Parliament led by house majority leader Aden Duale.</p>]]>
  </story>
  <author>
      <![CDATA[DPPS -1]]>
    </author>
  </article>

<media>
    <photo><![CDATA[http://cdn.marcellus.tv/0/xml/images/DNHague1610d.JPG.jpg]]></photo>
      <caption><![CDATA[

PHOTO | BILLY MUTAI Deputy President William Ruto and his daughter leave the International Criminal Court in The Hague on October 15, 2013.]]></caption>
      </media>
<link>
    http://www.nation.co.ke/news/politics/William-Ruto-Hague-ICC-Netherlands/-/1064/2058210/-/7qrqqwz/-/index.html</link>
</item><item>
<article>

    <section>
        <parent>News</parent>
        <child>Politics</child>
    </section>
  <title><![CDATA[Victims’ lawyer urges UN not to defer cases ]]></title>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <description><![CDATA[  The UN Security Council is set to hold its first plenary session sitting anytime this week in New York to discuss the AU request for the deferral of the cases facing President Kenyatta ]]></description>
  <articleDate>Saturday, November 2 2013 20:40:41 GMT+0200


</articleDate>
  <story>
      <![CDATA[  <p>The legal representative of the victims in President Uhuru Kenyatta case at the International Criminal Court in The Hague, Mr Fergal Gaynor has urged the UN Security Council to ignore the request for deferral of the cases facing  Mr Kenyatta by the African Union (AU).</p><p>The UN Security Council is set to hold its first plenary session sitting anytime this week in New York to discuss the AU request for the deferral of the cases facing President Kenyatta  and his deputy, Mr William Ruto, at  The Hague.</p><p>Mr Gaynor said any deferment will affect the victims.</p><p>“This would be a vote in favour of impunity. It will be a big tragedy because it will deny the victims justice after waiting for 21 months since the confirmation of the charges,” he said.</p><p>Mr Gaynor was answering questions via Skype from journalists attending a one-day Journalists Media Forum at a Kisumu hotel on Thursday.</p><p>The forum, organised by Journalists For Justice (JFJ) and the international Commission of Jurists (ICJ) Kenya Chapter, attracted more than 40 journalists from Rift Valley, Western and Nyanza regions.</p><p>Mr Gaynor said the government had put enormous resources to push for the deferral of the cases and forgotten to compensate the victims of the post elections violence in Nyanza and Western regions.</p><p>“The push by the government and the AU is not genuine, it’s not credible. People who were expelled from Naivasha and Nakuru and those who suffered atrocities in Western have been ignored and discriminated even in compensation,” said Mr Gaynor.</p><p>The legal representative said it would be a “tragic and  backward step” for the Security Council to postpone the case for 12 months.</p><p>Mr Gaynor said that so far no witness in the case he is handling has pulled out or shown any signs that they were willing to pull out.</p><p>He criticised the National Council of Churches of Kenya for supporting the deferment of the case.</p>]]>
  </story>
  <author>
      <![CDATA[ FRANCIS MUREITHI @FMUreith1 fmureithi@ke.nationmedia.com -1]]>
    </author>
  </article>

<media>
    <photo><![CDATA[http://cdn.marcellus.tv/0/xml/images/op3-pic.jpg]]></photo>
      <caption><![CDATA[

The International Criminal Court. The legal representative of the victims in President Uhuru Kenyatta case at the International Criminal Court in The Hague, Mr Fergal Gaynor has urged the UN Security Council to ignore the request for deferral of the cases facing  Mr Kenyatta by the African Union (AU). PHOTO|FILE]]></caption>
      </media>
<link>
    http://www.nation.co.ke/news/politics/Victims-lawyer-urges-UN-not-to-defer-cases-/-/1064/2057900/-/7gks74z/-/index.html</link>
</item><item>
<article>

    <section>
        <parent>News</parent>
        <child>Politics</child>
    </section>
  <title><![CDATA[US, Britain oppose bid to postpone Kenya cases ]]></title>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <description><![CDATA[  Rwanda, Togo and Morocco circulated a draft resolution for a deferral among UN Security Council members on Friday, but there are indications the request will be rejected.]]></description>
  <articleDate>Saturday, November 2 2013 20:37:15 GMT+0200


</articleDate>
  <story>
      <![CDATA[  <p>Kenya’s push to have the cases against President Uhuru Kenyatta and his deputy William Ruto deferred seems headed for failure after an informal gathering of the UN Security Council indicated it would turn down the request.</p><p>Rwanda, Togo and Morocco circulated a draft resolution for a deferral among UN Security Council members on Friday, but there are indications the request will be rejected.</p><p>Minutes from a lobbying meeting held among ministers of foreign affairs from countries sitting on the Security Council show that Kenya managed to secure the support of only five  of the 15 members. Only one of these has veto power.</p><p>At the meeting in Washington, eight ministers turned down the proposal while two others were non-committal.</p><p>Kenya’s Permanent Representative to the UN, Mr Macharia Kamau, Saturday said there are no specific dates when a decision by the Security Council can be expected. “However, it is anticipated that the decision will come within the fortnight,” he said.</p><p>It is expected that the views of the foreign affairs ministers will be reflected when the request is put to a vote.</p><p>Frustration kicked in towards the end of the meeting with Kenya’s Foreign Affairs Secretary Amina Mohamed saying that if Article 16 was not applied, it might as well be deleted from the Statute. </p><p>Article 16 states: “No investigation or prosecution may be commenced or proceeded with under this Statute for a period of 12 months after the Security Council, in a resolution adopted under Chapter VII of the Charter of the United Nations, has requested the Court to that effect; that request may be renewed by the Council under the same conditions.”</p><p>Ms Mohamed claimed that by refusing to grant a deferral, the council would be empowering those Kenya is fighting against (terrorists).</p><p>The minister asked how some Security Council members knew that President Kenyatta’s case would be postponed to February long before the decision was made public.</p><p>Rwanda’s representatives said they would table a resolution before the council even if a refusal was evident.</p><p>Ethiopia’s minister was also unimpressed, wondering why most countries held a similar position prior to the meeting. The minister accused Security Council members of having plotted in advance to reject Kenya’s request.</p><p>President Kenyatta and Mr Ruto are accused alongside radio journalist Joshua Sang of bearing the greatest responsibility for the 2007-2008 post-election violence that left 1,113 people dead and over 600,000 displaced.</p><p>Ms Mohamed has undertaken shuttle diplomacy to convince Security Council members to defer the cases for a year.</p><p>The council can order a deferral of a case if there is proof that its continuation would jeopardise international peace.</p><p>Kenya is citing the recent Westgate terrorist attack and the continuing peace efforts in Somalia by the Kenya Defence Forces to ask for a deferral.</p><p>To achieve such a deferral, though, it is necessary to convince at least nine of the 15 members of the powerful council to vote in their favour without a veto.</p><p>Countries that hold veto power are China, France, Russia, the UK and the US. Other countries that sit on the council but have no veto power are Argentina, Australia, Azerbaijan, Guatemala, Luxembourg, Morocco, Pakistan, Korea, Rwanda and Togo.</p><p>The only country holding veto power that backed Kenya’s request was China. Togo, Rwanda, Morocco and Azerbaijan also supported the deferral.</p><p>The US, the UK and France  were categorical in declining the request. Other countries that declined are Argentina, Australia, Guatemala, Luxembourg and South Korea. Russia and Pakistan gave half-hearted responses.</p><p>The minutes seen by the Sunday Nation indicate that the Chinese Foreign Affairs minister expressly suggested that the Security Council should invoke Article 16 and postpone the trial.</p><p>The French minister is quoted as saying that his country did not see a need to consider a deferral and emphasised judicial proceedings must proceed.</p><p>The matter should instead be handled by the Assembly of State Parties to the Rome Statute, the minister added. The minister was also concerned that deliberations of the meeting should not be negatively reflected in the media.</p><p>The US noted that the ICC had shown flexibility in proceedings, “which is good”. It decried witness intimidation as unacceptable and maintained that victims of the post-election violence needed justice. </p><p>The US also maintained that the matter should be dealt with through the assembly.</p><p>The UK minister noted that Article 16 was not the right vehicle, instead saying Britain was “looking forward” to addressing the matter through the Assembly of State Parties.</p><p>Guatemala’s minister said it was difficult to justify a deferral, adding that the role and interest of victims and witnesses was essential. The victims’ lawyers in the two cases have opposed a deferral.Luxembourg’s minister was more categorical noting that Article 16 could not apply since there is no threat to peace and security in Kenya.</p><p>The South Korean minister said the deferral clause should be invoked “only in exceptional circumstances” and backed the suggestion to address Kenya’s request through the assembly. </p><p>Argentina’s minister echoed the sentiments warning that a deferral is an “extremely exceptional measure” that is tantamount to “interference in an independent judicial body”.Australia also said the matter should be dealt with at the Assembly of State Parties which could consider amendments to the statute.</p><p>Russia sat on the fence, urging those in the parley to “calm down, wait and take it up in consultations”. Pakistan followed suit calling for a pragmatic solution. The country’s minister did not explicitly support use of Article 16, but stated that it would be possible.</p><p>Arguing Kenya’s case for deferral, Morocco’s minister underscored Kenya’s contribution to the peace process in Somalia. </p><p>Togo fully supported the deferral request, noting that although the assembly could handle the matter, it does not exempt the SC from giving a response</p><p>Azerbaijan offered unreserved support for deferral while Rwanda’s minister said the ICC decision to postpone the start of Mr Kenyatta’s case to February next year was late and shows polarisation of the court. </p><p>The minister said a lengthier period is required for Kenya to address the assembly and to deal with terrorism and other concerns. </p>]]>
  </story>
  <author>
      <![CDATA[KENFREY KIBERENGE -1]]>
    </author>
  </article>

<media>
    <photo><![CDATA[http://cdn.marcellus.tv/0/xml/images/566845-01-02_JPG.jpg]]></photo>
      <caption><![CDATA[

PHOTO | ELIAS ASMARE| FILE Kenyan President Uhuru Kenyatta (L) speaks with Cabinet secretary for Foreign Affairs Amina Mohammed (R), and Attorney General Githu Mungai (2-R) at the African Union ahead of a special summit on the continent's relationship with the International Criminal Court (ICC) on October 12, 2013.]]></caption>
      </media>
<link>
    http://www.nation.co.ke/news/politics/US-Britain-oppose-bid-to-postpone-Kenya-cases-/-/1064/2057890/-/6fydst/-/index.html</link>
</item><item>
<article>

    <section>
        <parent>Home</parent>
        <child>News</child>
    </section>
  <title><![CDATA[Uhuru welcomes debate on the proposed media law ]]></title>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <description><![CDATA[  President Uhuru Kenyatta has asked the media fraternity not to panic following the sailing through Parliament of a controversial media Bill on Thursday.]]></description>
  <articleDate>Saturday, November 2 2013 20:35:10 GMT+0200


</articleDate>
  <story>
      <![CDATA[  <p>President Uhuru Kenyatta has asked the media fraternity not to panic following the sailing through Parliament of a controversial media Bill on Thursday.</p><p>The President said Parliament as the legislative arm of government had done its duty but maintained that for any Bill to be signed into law, it must conform to the Constitution. </p><p>Speaking in Mashuuru, Kajiado County, during a thanks-giving ceremony for the election of Peris Pesi Tobiko as MP for Kajiado East constituency, Mr Kenyatta stated Saturday that nobody intended to gag the media.</p><p>At the same meeting, House Majority Leader Aden Duale promised to invite media practitioners for discussion about the law. </p><p>President Kenyatta said: “I shall look at the Bill once it is forwarded to me with a view to identifying and addressing possible grey areas to ensure the new media law conforms to the Constitution.” </p><p>However, the President advised journalists that freedom and responsibility go hand in hand, adding that free media should exercise professionalism, balance, fairness and decorum in news coverage. </p><p>DEATH KNELL</p><p>Mr Duale warned politicians against making political mileage out of the recently passed media Bill known as the Kenya Information and Communication Bill (2013) .</p><p>He said that the passing of the Communication Bill recently does not mark the death knell for a free media in the country.</p><p>Mr Duale asked why some parliamentarians in the opposition were quick to blame government for the passing of the Bill yet they failed to oppose the Motion on the floor of the house. He said that Parliament has no intention of introducing draconian laws to muzzle critical voices as alleged by the Opposition.</p><p>“We have no intention of gagging the media as this will be an affront to the freedom of expression which we all champion,” said Mr Duale.He said that the Jubilee government was committed to empowering women and the youth. </p><p>“We have put a lot of emphasis on women and youth empowerment. As a government we will continue to open leadership positions for them,” he said. </p><p>The President cited recent Cabinet appointments where women were given an opportunity to oversee key dockets including foreign affairs, defence, and devolution and planning among others. </p><p>President Kenyatta said that to further empower women, the government has opened up procurement laws so that 30 per cent of all government procurement opportunities are set aside for women, youth and disabled persons.  </p><p>“If all the women and youth in this country got opportunities to work with the government, we would reduce poverty,” he said, adding that “If you empower a woman you have empowered a family and the nation.” </p><p>The President also promised that the Mashuruu-Kajiado road would be rehabilitated. </p><p>Others who addressed the function included Kajiado Governor David Nkendienye, Senator Peter Mositet, Members of Parliament Joseph Nkaissery and Moses ole Sakuda.</p>]]>
  </story>
  <author>
      <![CDATA[PSCU -1]]>
    </author>
  </article>

<media>
    <photo><![CDATA[http://cdn.marcellus.tv/0/xml/images/DnTobikoUhuru0211.jpg]]></photo>
      <caption><![CDATA[

President Uhuru Kenyatta arrives at the a thanks giving ceremony of  the first Maasai female Member of Parliament Hon. Peris Tobiko in Kajiondo East, Kajiando County. PHOTO/PSCU]]></caption>
      </media>
<link>
    http://www.nation.co.ke/news/Uhuru-welcomes-debate-on-media-bill-law/-/1056/2057888/-/10vu8au/-/index.html</link>
</item><item>
<article>

    <section>
        <parent>News</parent>
        <child>Politics</child>
    </section>
  <title><![CDATA[Judiciary now takes on MPs ]]></title>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <description><![CDATA[  They also said they are aware of a threat by Parliament to cut the budgetary allocation of the Judiciary to force it to abandon or relax its drive to eliminate corruption.]]></description>
  <articleDate>Saturday, November 2 2013 20:34:30 GMT+0200


</articleDate>
  <story>
      <![CDATA[  <p>Judges and magistrates have questioned the move by some MPs to push for the removal of six members of the Judicial Service Commission over the sacking of High Court Chief Registrar Gladys Boss Shollei last month.</p><p>In a hard hitting statement issued at the Supreme Court, executive officials of the Kenya Magistrates and Judges Association said some MPs are bent on stalling the fight against corruption at the Judiciary.</p><p>They also said they are aware of a threat by Parliament to cut the budgetary allocation of the Judiciary to force it to abandon or relax its drive to eliminate corruption.</p><p>“Who is Parliament seeking to punish? How can justice be dispensed without important things like pens, paper, desks, water, toilets, notice boards, court rooms, chairs, etc. Wouldn’t Wanjiku, who voted for parliamentarians, end up paying the price? We are asking Kenyans to remain vigilant,” they said.</p><p>KMJA secretary-general Bryan Khaemba, deputy Chief Kadhi Rashid Ali Omar and deputy treasurer Mariam Mugure, said that unlike the past where the Judiciary was beholden to the whims of the Executive, it is now an independent institution.</p><p>He said the promulgation of Constitution in 2010 brought to a halt the days when the Executive and the Legislature used to control justice by reducing funds and making the Judiciary beg for budgetary allocations.</p><p>Last week, the Parliamentary Committee on Justice received accusations against some members of the JSC that they were not fit to hold public office and asking for their removal.</p><p>Chief Justice Dr Willy Mutunga, who chairs the JSC and is president of the Supreme Court said members of JSC will not appear before the parliamentary committee to be grilled over the sacking of Ms Shollei.</p><p>The CJ has already invited the Ethics and Anti-Corruption Commission (EACC) to investigate the misuse of Sh2.2 billion with a view to filing of criminal charges against anyone found culpable.</p><p>The association defended JSC in the sacking of Ms Shollei, saying the commission acted within the law.</p><p>Mrs Shollei has defended herself saying she has committed no wrong and that the JSC did not hear her out.</p><p>“The JSC never heard me. I have never admitted to any single charge. For the Chief Justice to say that, and the JSC, it is totally dishonest.” Mrs Shollei accused the commission and Dr Mutunga of subjecting her to a “kangaroo court.”</p><p> Dr Mutunga responded: “The fight against corruption is not a public relations exercise, it is a serious undertaking based only on facts.”</p><p>Mrs Shollei had said that no money was lost in the numerous transactions that the JSC has raised questions about. She also said there has been no corruption in the Judiciary.</p><p>The turf wars between Parliament and the Judiciary have been ongoing for the last two months, since the JSC started the process of removing Mrs Shollei from office.</p><p>The controversy deepened this week after the court order stopping MPs from debating a report on the conduct of JSC.</p><p>Justice George Odunga ruled that the departmental committee on Justice and Legal Affairs should not present to the National Assembly or hear a petition seeking to remove six commissioners from office.</p><p>“The court issues a conservatory order restraining deliberation of the report until the case is determined,” Justice Odunga said.</p><p>The judge ruled that issues raised by the JSC required a full hearing, adding that the High Court had powers over quasi-judicial committees and is empowered to stop the parliamentary committee from presenting its report for debate.</p><p>In the petition filed through lawyer Issa Mansur, the JSC claimed that the petition before the House was initiated in bad faith as a result of the decision to sack Mrs Gladys Shollei.</p><p>The commission’s legal counsel Wilfrida Mokaya swore that the committee’s chairman Samuel Chepkonga had been openly biased against them from the onset of their dispute with Mrs Shollei.</p>]]>
  </story>
  <author>
      <![CDATA[RICHARD MUNGUTI -1]]>
    </author>
  </article>

<media>
    <photo><![CDATA[http://cdn.marcellus.tv/0/xml/images/BD_JSC_1810.JPG.jpg]]></photo>
      <caption><![CDATA[

PHOTO | SALATON NJAU | FILE Chief Justice Willy Mutunga (centre), flanked by JSC members, addresses the media at the Supreme Court in Nairobi on October 18, 2013 when he announced the firing of Chief Registrar Gladys Shollei.]]></caption>
      </media>
<link>
    http://www.nation.co.ke/news/politics/Judiciary-now-takes-on-MPs-/-/1064/2057886/-/axbbctz/-/index.html</link>
</item><item>
<article>

    <section>
        <parent>News</parent>
        <child>Politics</child>
    </section>
  <title><![CDATA[Jubilee colleagues betrayed me: Ngilu]]></title>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <description><![CDATA[  It is instructive that Mrs Ngilu’s tribulations are being engineered by members of Jubilee.]]></description>
  <articleDate>Saturday, November 2 2013 20:33:34 GMT+0200


</articleDate>
  <story>
      <![CDATA[  <p>When President Uhuru Kenyatta appointed Mrs Charity Ngilu the Lands Cabinet Secretary about seven months ago, he offered her some advice.</p><p>“Charity, tengeneza hiyo mahali. (Charity, streamline that place),” President Kenyatta said in reference to the Lands ministry, which is dogged by some of the worst corruption, theft and fraud scandals the country has seen since independence.</p><p>Mrs Ngilu had in the Kibaki administration served in the Health as well as the Water and Irrigation dockets.</p><p>Seven months into her new job, Mrs Ngilu is a woman under siege.</p><p>This week, a report on her conduct in the ministry compiled by two parliamentary committees will be presented to the House in a move that may have far-reaching consequences for her career.</p><p>In an interview with the Sunday Nation on Friday, Mrs Ngilu spoke of a witch-hunt and betrayal by people she thought were colleagues in government.</p><p>It is instructive that Mrs Ngilu’s tribulations are being engineered by members of her Jubilee Coalition led by Leader of Majority in Parliament, Mr Adan Duale.</p><p>The investigation against Mrs Ngilu is led by Jubilee Coalition MPs who are the majority in the joint Committee of Lands and Delegated Legislation. The two committees are headed by MPs Alex Muiru and William Cheptumo. </p><p>The matter was first raised in Parliament by the vice-chairman of the Delegated Legislation committee, Mr Joseph Gitari. </p><p>In recommending that Mrs Ngilu be investigated, Mr Duale argued that the minister, together with other cabinet secretaries, should not be allowed to violate the Constitution.</p><p>“We are not in Somalia; there are laws in this country. I don’t want to stand here and protect ministers who live in the old days,” said Mr Duale before the issue was referred to the committees.</p><p>As Majority leader, Mr Duale is close to President Kenyatta and Deputy President William Ruto.</p><p>The Sunday Nation learned that Mrs Ngilu had met Mr Ruto last weekend to discuss her problems, but the outcome of their meeting is yet unknown. However, Mr Ruto is also said to have met Mr Duale and top Lands officials on the issue.</p><p>Sources said Mrs Ngilu was making frantic efforts to meet the President before the weekend as she struggles to keep her job.</p><p>“Ngilu’s position will largely depend on what she does at the weekend,” said an official familiar with the controversy, alluding to the fact that the minister’s sure option was to convince MPs not to recommend her removal from the Cabinet.</p><p>Mrs Ngilu’s appointment to the Cabinet was made courtesy of President Kenyatta’s TNA party, and she has privately said that URP was always opposed to her appointment. Mr Duale belongs to the URP wing.</p><p>So, is Mrs Ngilu’s viability in the Jubilee Cabinet half a year after she was appointed over? Has she outlived her usefulness?</p><p>URP secretary-general Fred Muteti denied reports that the party wanted Mrs Ngilu out. “On the floor of Parliament Mr Duale is playing his role as the Leader of Majority ... in any case we respect Mrs Ngilu. She is a performing cabinet secretary; we wish her a positive outcome from her current predicament.” </p><p>Mrs Ngilu says there is more than meets the eye in the goings on at her ministry which has dominated the headlines for all the wrong reasons over the past two weeks.</p><p>“There are landmines at the Lands ministry. How you survive them depends on how you dodge them,” she said.</p><p>“The truth of the matter is that there is a strong and powerful cartel at the ministry. The cartel has survived successive regimes. It is controlled by very rich individuals who can go to any length to ensure their interests prevail at whatever cost.”</p><p>She says there are people who have made money and continue to do so with impunity.</p><p>“If you try to cut their chain of supply they hit back,” she said.</p><p>“We have officials who are serving the interest of the government during the day and those of land cartels at night.” </p><p>The minister said most of her decisions at the ministry have been made in consultation with top officials.</p><p>“My decisions have never been unilateral but inclusive. For a leader to turn around and say that they were never involved at all is puzzling.”</p><p>Mrs Ngilu said she has been in Cabinet long enough and knew the problems bedevilling the Lands ministry when she took office.</p><p>“When I tried to carry on with the digitalisation process at the Lands ministry, I was frustrated. Some of our officials were in the forefront in destabilising the whole process. Those opposed to the plans knew that it would bring to an end the corruption in the system,” she says.</p><p>Asked what she plans to do to contain the cartels, Mrs Ngilu said: “Everything that has a beginning must have an end; their time will come, you cannot keep winning all the time.”</p><p>But even as the minister accused cartels of frustrating her, multiple sources in the ministry said she had taken office with a group of brokers in tow. In a way, it is the brokers’ zeal to make quick money that has landed her in the current situation.</p><p>The sources cited the scheme involving purported Kuwaiti government land in Westlands and other controversial decisions involving hundreds of acres of land in Athi River as some of the cases which could bring her down.   </p><p>On Thursday, Mrs Ngilu attended a Cabinet meeting chaired by President Kenyatta. Asked if the Head of State was aware of her predicament, she said: “I doubt it.”</p><p>Mrs Ngilu’s tribulations at the ministry came to the fore when she unilaterally created the office of the director-general and appointed former Coast lands officer Peter Kang’ethe Kahuho in  whom she vested the power to sign land title deeds. She reversed the decision a few days later as the political storm gathered over her move.</p><p>Previously the Commissioner of Lands had the sole powers to sign titles.</p><p>The move led Mrs Ngilu to be questioned by MPs who accused her of breaking the law by creating the office.</p><p>Mbooni MP Michael Kisoi Munyao, who sits in one of the committees investigating Mrs Ngilu, said they had completed their job and the report they arrived at will be presented to the House on Tuesday.</p><p>“Our task was to recommend action, not censure. We suggested that one, the minister de-gazette the appointment of Mr Kahuho and to reinstate all those who were sacked, and two, that she should fast-track the regulation on land reforms and bring it to Parliament so as to harmonise sensitive issues like titles deeds and separation of powers that is still a burning issue,” said Mr Munyao.</p><p>He was at one point ordered out of the parliamentary committee sittings for alleged misconduct.</p><p>He told the Sunday Nation that powerful individuals want Mrs Ngilu out of the Lands ministry.</p><p>“During the sittings that saw me forced out by the chairman, it was obvious that some members had a fixed mind regarding the type of verdict to be meted out on Ngilu. To me it appeared that the die had been cast. My interventions were rudely rejected and I was ordered out,” said the MP.</p><p>Mr Munyao said there is a powerful cartel at the Lands ministry that is pulling strings behind the scenes.</p><p>“The influence of the cartel is felt all over. I won’t be surprised if some of us are in league with them,” he said.</p><p>Mr Munyao expressed fears that there is a scheme by MPs opposed to Mrs Ngilu to introduce the word “censure” in their report on Tuesday.</p><p>“If this is done, then Mrs Ngilu will be in hot soup,” he said. </p><p>“In Parliament there is the Cord brigade that has not forgiven her for backing the Jubilee Coalition in the run-up to the March 4 General Election. Then there is a group of Jubilee MPs who also want her out. This combination can be devastating.”</p><p>Sunday Nation asked Mrs Ngilu whether her bosses were aware of her actions in the ministry given that former Lands Commissioner Zablon Mabea was a presidential appointee.</p><p>The minister said she had consulted widely. </p><p>“I just can’t wake up one day and force my decisions on people the way some fellows want it to appear.” </p><p>Asked why she has been left to stand alone, Mrs Ngilu replied: “It’s betrayal.”</p><p> She said Mr Mabea had told her that he was sick and could not perform his job effectively with regard to signing of titles.</p><p>“But Mr Mabea disowned me when he appeared before the commission, saying he was as fit as a fiddle,” said Mrs Ngilu.</p><p> Mr Mabea could not be reached for comment.</p>]]>
  </story>
  <author>
      <![CDATA[BOB ODALO  -1]]>
    </author>
  </article>

<media>
    <photo><![CDATA[http://cdn.marcellus.tv/0/xml/images/DN+NGILU+0309+C.JPG.jpg]]></photo>
      <caption><![CDATA[

PHOTO | FILE Lands Cabinet Secretary Charity Ngilu. She has lamented that her colleagues in the Jubilee government.]]></caption>
      </media>
<link>
    http://www.nation.co.ke/news/politics/Jubilee-colleagues--betrayed-me-Ngilu/-/1064/2057882/-/u4wvrg/-/index.html</link>
</item><item>
<article>

    <section>
        <parent>Home</parent>
        <child>News</child>
    </section>
  <title><![CDATA[Mutunga wants Busia rape suspects arrested]]></title>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <description><![CDATA[  Chief Justice Willy Mutunga has demanded immediate action in the gang-rape case of the Busia pupil whose plight has attracted global attention.]]></description>
  <articleDate>Saturday, November 2 2013 19:23:54 GMT+0200


</articleDate>
  <story>
      <![CDATA[  <p>Chief Justice Willy Mutunga has demanded immediate action in the gang-rape case of the Busia pupil whose plight has attracted global attention.</p><p>Dr Mutunga has asked the National Council for the Administration of Justice to take up the matter.</p><p>“JusticeForLiz: “I have sent matter to the National Council for the Administration of Justice for immediate action,” he said in a tweet at the weekend.</p><p>The council was set-up  to coordinate and speed up administration of justice as well as address public grievances relating to security and access to justice.</p><p>Chaired by the Chief Justice, and Judiciary Registrar as secretary, the council comprises the Attorney General, Githu Muigai, Inspector-General of Police David Kimaiyo, the Director of Public Prosecutions Keriako Tobiko, the Commandant of Prisons and cLaw Society of Kenya chairman Eric Mutua.</p><p>Other members are Head of the  Public Service Joseph Kinyua, chairperson of the Kenya National Commission of Human Rights, the Gender Commission and the head of the Witness Protection Agency.</p><p>The rape and violent attack of the Standard Seven girl from Tingolo, in Butula on June 26 and failure to take action against the perpetrators has sparked public outrage with more than 1.2 million people across the world signing a petition demanding justice for the teenager.</p><p>Liz who is now wheel-chair bound is receiving treatment at Gynocare Fistula Centre in Eldoret for a spinal damage, obstetric fistula and post-traumatic stress disorder.  Her family says her attackers threw her into a pit latrine to conceal their crime.</p><p>The petition was created by Kenyan youth Nebila Abdulmelik, of the African Women’s Communication Network (Femnet) through the international campaign group Avaaz.</p><p>On Thursday,  more than 300 protestors demanding justice for the 16-year old marched through the streets of Nairobi to the offices Inspector General of police where they handed out the petition.</p><p>Dubbed “keep off our panties’’ the protestors also demanded arrest and prosecution of the six suspects and action against Administration Police officers  from Tingolo who released three of the suspects after making them slash grass in the police compound as punishment.</p>]]>
  </story>
  <author>
      <![CDATA[NJERI RUGENE -1]]>
    </author>
  </article>

<media>
    <photo><![CDATA[http://cdn.marcellus.tv/0/xml/images/mutungaWILLY.jpg]]></photo>
      <caption><![CDATA[

Chief Justice Dr Willy Mutunga. has demanded immediate action in the gang-rape case of the Busia pupil whose plight has attracted global attention. Photo/EMMA NZIOKA/FILE]]></caption>
      </media>
<link>
    http://www.nation.co.ke/news/Mutunga-wants-Busia-rape-suspects-arrested/-/1056/2057754/-/1q67fdz/-/index.html</link>
</item><item>
<article>

    <section>
        <parent>News</parent>
        <child>Politics</child>
    </section>
  <title><![CDATA[Activities galore as Machakos prepares to host Head of State ]]></title>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <description><![CDATA[  The launch of the new Machakos City and investment programme is set for Wednesday when the President will lay the foundation stone for the new site overlooking Maruba Dam. ]]></description>
  <articleDate>Saturday, November 2 2013 19:22:57 GMT+0200


</articleDate>
  <story>
      <![CDATA[  <p>Machakos Governor Alfred Mutua will this week host President Uhuru Kenyatta when the Head of State visits the region to help lay the county’s path to greater socio-economic growth.</p><p>The launch of the new Machakos City and investment programme is set for Wednesday when the President will lay the foundation stone for the new site overlooking Maruba Dam. </p><p>But the date may change if President Kenyatta proceeds on a previously planned official travel to South Africa Monday.</p><p>“We are changing the way things are done,” Dr Mutua told the Sunday Nation. “We are transforming ideas that we have had for years into action so as to fight poverty. In life you are judged not by what you say you want to do but what you actually do to help humanity.”</p><p>Dr Mutua believes that a new city will be the necessary magnet to attract investors to the county “so as to grow the economy and provide badly needed jobs”. Machakos has so far attracted thousands of investors who have signed a memorandum of understanding with investment values close to Sh1.53 trillion. Most of the investors have been attracted by Dr Mutua’s promise of free land for investment.</p><p>“When you want to develop, you look at what resources you have and how to maximise on them,” he said. “We do not have oil or major minerals in Machakos County, but we have an able workforce, excellent weather and land.”</p><p>The Machakos plan is to provide  land to investors who would then build hospitals, factories, universities, economic zones, CBD buildings and even sports centres. Priority will be given to companies that are able to start work immediately.</p><p>Dr Mutua said Machakos town has 2,200 acres set aside for urban development. This land was previously owned by the now defunct Machakos Municipality. The land is next to another piece of about 1,000 acres that belongs to the veterinary laboratory. But it is the county land only that will be used for investment together with another 2,000 acres spread across the county.</p><p>“We are not touching the veterinary lab land,” Dr Mutua said. “But we hope to negotiate with them in the future for a gift of the land. We will work with what we have first.”</p><p>The Governor said his initiative is expected to create 120,000 direct jobs and a total of 360,000 indirect jobs and contribute significantly to the economy of Kenya to achieve the double-digit growth promised by the Jubilee Government. Already, major investors from Kenya, Uganda, Tanzania, Rwanda, Nigeria, South Africa, Italy, France, India, Dubai, Oman, Japan, China, South Korea, Brazil, Canada, Australia, United States and England have confirmed attendance at the launch.</p><p>“President Kenyatta is very sharp,” said Dr Mutua. “He knows that the bureaucracy, haggling and sabotage, common in African countries, are what have rendered Africans poor. As a visionary, together with his ‘digital’ mate, Deputy President William Ruto, he sees the big picture and supports it, and we support his development plans and new way of doing things.”</p><p>It has been six months since Governor Mutua took office. For him it has been a race against time as he embarked on one project after another. Currently there are five major ambitious projects going on simultaneously in the county, coupled with many smaller ones.</p><p>The President’s visit to the town will be the first of its kind following an invitation by a governor since the March 4 General Election. </p><p>On October 30, Dr Mutua launched an agricultural subsidy programme based some 70 km from the county headquarters at Kithimani in Matuu area.</p><p>The programme aims to identify  and provide solutions to the problem of food insecurity which has been synonymous with the mainly semi-arid and arid region since independence 50 years ago.</p>]]>
  </story>
  <author>
      <![CDATA[BOB ODALO  -1]]>
    </author>
  </article>

<media>
    <photo><![CDATA[http://cdn.marcellus.tv/0/xml/images/dnAlfredMutua1709.jpg]]></photo>
      <caption><![CDATA[

Machakos governor Dr. Alfred Mutua walks in the streets of Machakos accompanied by Makueni Senator Mutula Kilonzo Jnr. Photo/FILE]]></caption>
      </media>
<link>
    http://www.nation.co.ke/news/politics/-/1064/2057752/-/wgyrq4/-/index.html</link>
</item><item>
<article>

    <section>
        <parent>News</parent>
        <child>Politics</child>
    </section>
  <title><![CDATA[Uhuru to leave for SA as Ruto jets in to run State affairs  ]]></title>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <description><![CDATA[  President Uhuru Kenyatta heads to South Africa on a three-day official visit as talks to defer the Kenya ICC cases continue at the United Nations.]]></description>
  <articleDate>Saturday, November 2 2013 19:20:48 GMT+0200


</articleDate>
  <story>
      <![CDATA[  <p>President Uhuru Kenyatta heads to South Africa on a three-day official visit as talks to defer the Kenya ICC cases continue at the United Nations.</p><p>The President’s expected absence from Monday necessitated the ICC to grant his deputy William Ruto leave from the court for a week just two days after being in court in person. Mr Ruto will be in charge of government affairs in the President’s absence until Wednesday.</p><p>The Trial Chamber V (a) also allowed Mr Ruto to miss the sittings on Thursday and Friday as he will be chairing a refugee and drought meeting in Nairobi.</p><p>Presiding judge Chile Eboe-Osuji said that the decision to grant the request was unanimous. “The Chamber has deliberated on the Ruto request,” Mr Osuji said on Friday. “The chamber unanimously grants the request,” the judge said.</p><p>The court will give the formal reasons on Monday. Mr Ruto’s excusal came just a day after the chamber rejected Joshua Sang’s application to be allowed to attend his daughter’s graduation on Friday.</p><p>Kenya has been leading a diplomatic onslaught at the UN to have the cases against President Kenyatta and Mr Ruto deferred for at least a year, with the possibility of extension.</p><p>The deferral request is supported by the African Union on the basis of the country’s role in the fight against terrorism in the region. Kenya and the AU also cite the strides the country has made in constitutional and institutional reforms since the 2007 election chaos to prove its case for a deferral. </p><p>Meanwhile, the ICC is contemplating carrying on with the proceedings against Mr Ruto and Mr Sang after President Kenyatta’s case was delayed until February next year. </p><p>“Kenyatta case has now been adjourned over to February. We need to discuss the implication of that before we adjourn this session whether we can use the opportunity in the Ruto case,” judge Osuji said Friday.</p><p>The prosecution and the victims legal representative have welcomed the chamber’s move, asking that the parties only get about two weeks break from Friday November 8. In other words, they were pointing at the possibility of having the trials resume at least by November 18 until December 13 when the court takes its winter recess.  </p><p>Lead trial lawyer Anton Steynberg said the prosecution was in a position to line up to three witnesses during that period.</p><p>“It should be logistically possible to line up three short witnesses before the winter recess,” said Mr Steynberg.</p><p>However, the defence teams of Mr Ruto and Mr Sang have opposed the resumption of the trials anytime this year, arguing that that would be prejudicial to their clients.</p><p>Mr Karim Khan for the deputy president went as far as suggesting that the chamber was treating his client’s case as a “filler”. </p><p>Both the defence teams and the prosecution are however agreed that trials resume on January 13 while the victims wanted the resumption set for January 6. The chamber has yet to communicate its decision. </p>]]>
  </story>
  <author>
      <![CDATA[Walter Menya -1]]>
    </author>
  </article>

<media>
    <photo><![CDATA[http://cdn.marcellus.tv/0/xml/images/uhuruto.jpg]]></photo>
      <caption><![CDATA[

President Uhuru Kenyatta shares a word with his deputy William Ruto at a past function. Photo/FILE]]></caption>
      </media>
<link>
    http://www.nation.co.ke/news/politics/Uhuru-to-leave-for-SA-as-Ruto-jets-in-to-run-State-affairs--/-/1064/2057750/-/xqmm2x/-/index.html</link>
</item><item>
<article>

    <section>
        <parent>News</parent>
        <child>Politics</child>
    </section>
  <title><![CDATA[House team wants agency given powers to ban newspapers ]]></title>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <description><![CDATA[  A parliamentary committee has proposed new laws that would give the Media Council powers to ban newspapers and punish readers found with banned publications.]]></description>
  <articleDate>Saturday, November 2 2013 19:19:3 GMT+0200


</articleDate>
  <story>
      <![CDATA[  <p>A parliamentary committee has proposed new laws that would give the Media Council powers to ban newspapers and punish readers found with banned publications.</p><p>The proposal comes just days after Parliament voted for a Bill introducing measures to gag the media.</p><p>The proposed amendments to the Media Council of Kenya Bill also seek to introduce sweeping powers to ban publications for ambiguous reasons couched in the Bill as national interest, public order, morality and threat to security.</p><p>Cartoons would also come under scrutiny under the new proposals. </p><p>They come in the wake of a controversy between the government and the media over the coverage of the Westgate Mall attack and especially the publication of footage of Kenya Defence Forces officers looting shops there. </p><p>MPs want the power to determine who sits on the council done through a parliamentary vetting process that analysts say would likely make the appointees beholden to politicians.</p><p>The Energy, Information and Communications Committee chaired by Kigumo MP Jamleck Kamau has suggested the new rules in amendments to be made to the Media Council of Kenya Bill at the Third Reading. </p><p>In the amendments, the committee wants the media watchdog to be given powers to license the publication of newspapers and terminate or suspend their permits.</p><p>It is proposed that the Media Council also exercise the power to grant permits to print, publish and circulate newspapers. </p><p>Similarly, anyone found printing, selling or circulating a paper whose permit has been revoked or terminated would be committing an offence and could be jailed for up to two years or fined up to Sh10 million or both upon conviction.</p><p>The amendments also seek to punish readers of such banned newspapers with anyone found in possession of such publications to be imprisoned for a term not exceeding two months or fined up to Sh10,000, or both.</p><p>DEEM PREJUDICIAL</p><p>The committee further proposes withdrawal of a the permit of any publication whose content the council may deem “prejudicial or likely to be prejudicial to public order, public interest or national interest.”</p><p>“The Council, if satisfied, may, by order published in the Gazette, withdraw the licence to print, import, produce, reproduce, publish, sell, issue, circulate, distribute or possession of that publication and future publications of the publisher concerned,” reads the proposals.</p><p>The present Media Council is a self-regulatory body primarily charged with adjudicating complaints against journalists and publishers relating to their professional code of conduct.</p><p>It is funded by the government but maintains its independence through a self-governing complaints commission and an appointment process controlled by the media industry.</p><p>Yesterday, the council said it was not aware of the proposals.</p><p>Council chairman Joseph Odindo said the watchdog’s main mandate is to arbitrate on issues raised in the code of conduct for journalists and that power to grant permits is outside its authority.</p><p>“The council does not ban media houses or suspend journalists, and it has never desired to do so,” Mr Odindo said.</p><p>He added that provisions to deal with reports or articles considered prejudicial to public order, morality, security or those considered likely to alarm public opinion should be left to the law and not a council or a tribunal.</p><p>The House committee has also proposed changes to the manner in which the selection panel that will interview applicants for positions in the Media Council will process their final decisions.</p><p>The panel shall be required to select three people qualified for the position of chairman and six others as members and forward their names to the Cabinet secretary.</p><p>Within seven days, the minister shall forward the name of one person as chairman and the six as members for vetting by the National Assembly. If the MPs are satisfied with the nominees, they shall notify the Cabinet secretary, who will then appoint the nominees.</p><p>This development comes barely two days after Parliament came up with a Media Bill considered very repressive.</p><p>STATE CONTROLLED</p><p>The passage of the Kenya Information and Media Bill shifted the adjudication of complaints against media from the Media Council to a new government controlled agency with power to ban journalists from practising and to impose fines of up to Sh20 million on media houses that  breach the code of conduct.</p><p>The media industry and lawyers have pointed out that the new Bill, which now awaits presidential approval or rejection, is not in conformity with the Constitution.</p><p>The head of legal services at Nation Media Group, Sekou Owino, said the two Bills undermined the constitutional requirement of a free media.</p><p>“Article 34 of the Constitution is clear that the State shall not control or interfere with any media establishment. The article adds that any regulatory body with authority over the broadcasting and electronic media shall be independent of control by government or any commercial or political interest,” he said.</p><p>The Media Council Bill is scheduled for the Second Reading on Tuesday where MPs will discuss possible changes while relying on the report of the committee tabled in the House on Tuesday. </p><p>The actual amendments would be made at the Third Reading where MPs  vote on each clause of the proposed law while inserting any changes proposed either by the committee or individuals.</p><p>The committee seeks to create an opportunity for politicians to be appointed to media regulatory bodies by proposing a deletion of the provision that someone who “has at any time within the preceding five years, held a political office” would be ineligible for appointment as a chairperson or member of the Media Council.</p><p>“The committee is of the opinion politicians should also be considered as professionals who can give leadership in any public body, commission or council,” the committee says.</p><p>It has also proposed a minor amendment of a part of the proposed law to differentiate between the two Houses of Parliament and to make the Council’s finances known to the public through the National Assembly. </p><p>The media has been critical of sections of the Media Council Bill that empower the Cabinet secretary to dissolve the current council, declare vacancies and then select the panel to interview candidates.</p>]]>
  </story>
  <author>
      <![CDATA[PETER OBUYA -1]]>
    </author>
  </article>

<media>
    <photo><![CDATA[http://cdn.marcellus.tv/0/xml/images/PIX1.jpg]]></photo>
      <caption><![CDATA[

Energy, Communication and Information committee Chairman Jamleck Kamau. PHOTO/ FILE]]></caption>
      </media>
<link>
    http://www.nation.co.ke/news/politics/House-team-wants-agency-given-powers-to-ban-newspapers-/-/1064/2057748/-/2wbu34/-/index.html</link>
</item><item>
<article>

    <section>
        <parent>News</parent>
        <child>World</child>
    </section>
  <title><![CDATA[Taliban attack US drone after strike ]]></title>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <description><![CDATA[  Tribesmen opened fire on a US drone over Pakistan’s troubled tribal belt Saturday, where Pakistani Taliban commander Hakimullah Mehsud was killed by a drone strike, residents and officials said.]]></description>
  <articleDate>Saturday, November 2 2013 19:17:44 GMT+0200


</articleDate>
  <story>
      <![CDATA[  <p>Tribesmen opened fire on a US drone over Pakistan’s troubled tribal belt Saturday, where Pakistani Taliban commander Hakimullah Mehsud was killed by a drone strike, residents and officials said.</p><p>Mehsud, who had a $5 million US government bounty on him, died along with four others on Friday when a US drone fired two missiles at a vehicle in a compound in the village of Dandey Darpakhel, five kilometres north of Miranshah, the main town of North Waziristan.</p><p>His death came as a major blow to the militant network and cast doubt over proposed peace talks, with fears of reprisals.</p><p>Local residents told AFP that dozens of tribesmen and militants had opened fire on a US drone which was flying low in the same area where the Taliban chief was killed.</p><p>“Tribesmen and militants were firing with light and heavy guns for an hour,” Tariq Khan, a shopkeeper in Miranshah told AFP.</p><p>BURRIED LATE FRIDAY</p><p>A security official in Miranshah confirmed the firing. </p><p>The official and residents said Mehsud was buried late Friday along with the four others killed — his bodyguard, driver, uncle and a commander, according to a senior Taliban source.</p><p>The usually busy Miranshah bazaar opened on Saturday but shoppers stayed at home.  “Local people are scared.” Mr Khan said.    </p>]]>
  </story>
  <author>
      <![CDATA[AFP -1]]>
    </author>
  </article>

<media>
    <photo><![CDATA[http://cdn.marcellus.tv/0/xml/images/EADronesa.jpg]]></photo>
      <caption><![CDATA[

US drone. Tribesmen opened fire on a US drone over Pakistan’s troubled tribal belt Saturday, where Pakistani Taliban commander Hakimullah Mehsud was killed by a drone strike, residents and officials said. PHOTO/AFP]]></caption>
      </media>
<link>
    http://www.nation.co.ke/news/world/Taliban-attack-US-drone-after-strike-/-/1068/2057742/-/85if41z/-/index.html</link>
</item><item>
<article>

    <section>
        <parent>News</parent>
        <child>World</child>
    </section>
  <title><![CDATA[Obama tells Congress resolve ‘artificial crisis’ ]]></title>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <description><![CDATA[  The US deficit for the fiscal year 2013, which ended September 30, stood at 4.1 per cent of gross domestic product, the Treasury Department announced Wednesday.]]></description>
  <articleDate>Saturday, November 2 2013 19:15:52 GMT+0200


</articleDate>
  <story>
      <![CDATA[  <p>President Barack Obama Saturday called for an end to “manufactured crises and self-inflicted wounds” as he urged Republicans and Democrats in Congress to approve a new federal budget.</p><p>Mr Obama, speaking in his weekly radio address, said what most people hear out of Washington is “a jumble of unfocused noise that’s out of touch with the things you care about.</p><p>“So today, I want to cut through that noise and talk plainly about what we should do right now,” he said.</p><p>“It begins by ending what has done more than anything else to undermine our economy over the past few years - and that’s the constant cycle of manufactured crises and self-inflicted wounds.”</p><p>Mr Obama spoke a little more than two weeks after the United States scraped through a bitter budget and debt ceiling battle that threatened to send the country into default and forced the 16-day partial federal government shutdown, but only by using stop-gap measures that pushed the battle deadlines forward.</p><p>If a fresh budget deal is not found by January 15, when the temporary funding expires, a new round of automatic spending cuts will hit.</p><p>Obama said Congress should “pass a budget that cuts things we don’t need, and closes wasteful tax loopholes that don’t help create jobs so that we can free up resources for the things that actually do create jobs and growth.”</p><p>The president also had something to boast about, noting that this week “the Treasury confirmed that since I took office, we’ve cut our deficits by more than half.”</p><p>The US deficit for the fiscal year 2013, which ended September 30, stood at 4.1 per cent of gross domestic product, the Treasury Department announced Wednesday.</p><p>The deficit-to-GDP ratio was 7.0 per cent in 2012. </p>]]>
  </story>
  <author>
      <![CDATA[AFP -1]]>
    </author>
  </article>

<media>
    <photo><![CDATA[http://cdn.marcellus.tv/0/xml/images/OBAMA_PIX.jpg]]></photo>
      <caption><![CDATA[

PHOTO | AFP US President Barack Obama. ]]></caption>
      </media>
<link>
    http://www.nation.co.ke/news/world/Obama-tells-Congress-resolve-artificial-crisis/-/1068/2057736/-/99983lz/-/index.html</link>
</item><item>
<article>

    <section>
        <parent>News</parent>
        <child>Africa</child>
    </section>
  <title><![CDATA[Africa crises grow in fight to save Kenya from Hague ]]></title>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <description><![CDATA[  A lot of homework awaits African leaders who need to move away from costly self-preservation games and address myriad crises bedevilling the continent. ]]></description>
  <articleDate>Saturday, November 2 2013 19:14:40 GMT+0200


</articleDate>
  <story>
      <![CDATA[  <p>It was certainly the week that was as the world focused on the United Nations Security Council deliberations on the spat between the African Union and Kenya on the one hand, and the Hague-based International Criminal Court on the other.</p><p>The international drama aside, back at home, a lot of homework awaits African leaders who need to move away from costly self-preservation games and address myriad crises bedevilling the continent. </p><p>Now the order of the day, the crises in the troubled continent are still simmering, with many of them threatening to get out of hand.</p><p>Gratefully though, in DR Congo, the M 23 rebels appeared to be on the verge of being finally vanquished.  </p><p>In fact, President Joseph Kabila was reported to have been able to finally re-establish his authority in the formerly irksome North Kivu region that had been steeped in anarchy thanks to M 23 terror. </p><p>Signs of final peace were showing after 20 months of intermittent fighting and stalled negotiations that have had regional leaders meeting regularly without  making any breakthroughs in the perennial Congolese crisis.</p><p>HUMANITARIAN CRISIS </p><p>The result has been a major humanitarian crisis that has seen refugees spreading out in the entire region and across borders into neighbouring countries. In the meantime, the rebellion led by the M23 has been able to control a string of towns in the eastern region of the country, reportedly enriching its leaders as they looted mineral resources in the areas they controlled.</p><p>Next door, in the Central African Republic, things are not looking too good. In the past few weeks, rising fatalities have been reported there as a state of insecurity persists despite efforts by former colonial master France to  play prefect and restore order.</p><p>Across in Sudan, the controversial Abyei region finally went into a contested referendum that was declared a virtual ‘declaration of war’.</p><p>Organised by the South Sudan-allied Ng’ok Dinka, the majority of who want to join South Sudan, the unilateral referendum was to determine the status of the region.</p><p>FRESH CLASHES </p><p>Just about a week ago, there were fresh clashes there between the Sudanese Armed Forces (SAF) and the so-called rebels of the  Sudan Liberation Movement (SLM) headed by Abdul Whaid Alnour. The death toll on both sides included, as usual, scores of civilians.</p><p>The move had been firmly opposed by the Messiriya people allied to Sudan— herders who seasonally migrate into the region from Sudan.</p><p>They firmly rejected the results of the unilateral referendum that was carried out despite AU warnings about its illegality.</p><p>In fact, the United Nations Security Council and the governments of South Sudan and Sudan had earlier stated that the unilateral vote was not a political solution to the status of the area. As for the AU visit to Abyei, it was aimed at defusing tension on the ground, including averting any unilateral actions. </p><p>Also aimed at creating a conducive environment for the peaceful resolution of the final status of the region,  the AU visit to Abyei was initially scheduled for October 22 and 23, but was deferred due to the presidential summit between President Salva Kiir and his Sudan counterpart, Omar Al-Bashir on October 22. </p><p>In what has played out as a perpetual theatre of the absurd, the two heads of state have been involved in mostly fruitless negotiations for years. Not surprisingly, their latest summit failed to resolve the long-standing issue of the Abyei referendum. </p><p>Predictably, the two leaders only agreed to install an Abyei joint administration, legislative council and the area police. Ironically though, those same matters had been  reportedly agreed on in the previous meetings but of course not been  implemented.</p><p>Abyei, once oil-rich but with production now on the downturn, now seems set to be the next theatre of intensified war in an already troubled region. </p><p>Virtually lawless, it is steeped in anarchy, and listens to nobody. In fact, just last Sunday an African Union delegation was prevented from visiting the area for what were said by the Sudan government to be “security reasons”.</p><p>Last week Misseriya leader Mukhtar Babo Nimir reportedly said his people had the option of also holding their own unilateral referendum if, as they have now done, the rival Ng’ok Dinka hold their own ballot. </p><p>The Abyei region was supposed to vote on whether to be part of Sudan or South Sudan in January 2011, when Juba voted overwhelmingly to break away from the north as part of the 2005 peace deal which ended Sudan’s civil war.</p><p>Repeatedly stalled, the failed referendum saw over 100,000 people fleeing the region in May 2011 and entering South Sudan as Abyei became a major hotspot in the African continent. </p><p>Not short of crises, Sudan is also home to the troubled Darfur region, where civilian fatalities have become the order of the day. Virtually lawless, the region has over the years defied peace efforts by the United Nations and the African Union.</p>]]>
  </story>
  <author>
      <![CDATA[CIUGU MWAGIRU ciugumwagiru@yahoo.co.uk -1]]>
    </author>
  </article>

<media>
    <photo><![CDATA[http://cdn.marcellus.tv/0/xml/images/op3-pic.jpg]]></photo>
      <caption><![CDATA[

The International Criminal Court.  PHOTO|FILE]]></caption>
      </media>
<link>
    http://www.nation.co.ke/news/africa/Africa-crises-grow-in-fight-to-save-Kenya-from-Hague-/-/1066/2057734/-/ulxm2oz/-/index.html</link>
</item><item>
<article>

    <section>
        <parent>News</parent>
        <child>Africa</child>
    </section>
  <title><![CDATA[Mugabe says Tsvangirai is  mad and liar ]]></title>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <description><![CDATA[  President Mugabe Sturday said his rival was making futile visits to Nigerian evangelist TB Joshua, seeking prayers in a bid to discredit his victory.]]></description>
  <articleDate>Saturday, November 2 2013 19:13:44 GMT+0200


</articleDate>
  <story>
      <![CDATA[  <p>Zimbabwe President Robert Mugabe has launched fresh attacks on opposition leader Morgan Tsvangirai, describing him as a mad man for refusing to accept election defeat on July 31.</p><p>President Mugabe Sturday said his rival was making futile visits to Nigerian evangelist TB Joshua, seeking prayers in a bid to discredit his victory.</p><p>“We won elections, now Mr Tsvangirai is running around saying he was cheated,” he said. “I don’t think he is normal. He is as good as mad.” </p><p>The 89 year-old leader said the former prime minister had also travelled to London to discredit the ruling Zanu PF party. </p><p>“He is running to London and has been to TB Joshua seeking prayers,” he said.  “But you cannot pray for a person who is bent on wrong-doing.</p><p>“He knows he lost but he says we stole the vote. If someone tells such lies and goes to the pastor to say pray for me, God will not listen to such a prayer.</p><p>“You know you are telling a lie and you kneel down asking God to give you blessings.</p><p>“Unless you know how to be honest, truthful and frank and admit your mistakes, God will not listen to you. </p><p>“We also pray for our own mistakes. We won and the whole world knows that except the British and the United States who tell lies like (Mr) Tsvangirai.” </p><p>The Movement for Democratic Change is a regular visitor to TB Joshua’s Synagogue Church of All Nations (SCOAN).</p><p>Video footage that showed Mr Tsvangirai losing his balance after the Nigerian touched his shoulder went viral on the internet last month.</p>]]>
  </story>
  <author>
      <![CDATA[Kitsepile Nyathi -1]]>
    </author>
  </article>

<media>
    <photo><![CDATA[http://cdn.marcellus.tv/0/xml/images/445338-01-02.JPG.jpg]]></photo>
      <caption><![CDATA[

PHOTO | JEKESAI NJIKIZANA | FILE Zimbabwe President Robert Mugabe speaks during a past rally.]]></caption>
      </media>
<link>
    http://www.nation.co.ke/news/africa/Mugabe-says-Tsvangirai-is--mad-and-liar-/-/1066/2057732/-/ffla1dz/-/index.html</link>
</item></channel>